Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Division of Research in the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1930-1968 UA.90.4.1.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh Division of Research in the Natural Sciences Office Files
1930-1968
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Division of Research in the Natural Sciences
UA.90.4.1.2
8.4 Linear Feet (20 boxes)
From 1944 to 1956, the Division of Research in the Natural Sciences was a centralized administrative office that organized and supported research activities of natural science departments and faculty. This collection contains correspondence and reports pertaining to natural science faculty, facilities, and research during the existence of the Division.
History
In 1936, the Buhl Foundation initiated a grant to support natural science research at the University of Pittsburgh. At the onset of World War II, the university also received government contracts in these fields, which necessitated the unified management of grant funds, resources, personnel, and facilities. In 1944, Vice Chancellor Rufus Fitzgerald addressed this need by creating the Division of Research in the Natural Sciences as a centralized administrative office to organize and support research activities in biology, chemistry, physics, geology, psychology, mathematics, astronomy, and related fields. Dr. Herbert E. Longenecker was named the first Dean of the division and he was succeeded by Acting Dean Max A. Lauffer in July 1955. The following year, the undergraduate College was reorganized into three disciplines and this division formed the foundation of the new Division of Natural Sciences with Dr. Lauffer as its Dean.
Acquisition Information
These records were deposited by Margaret Mary Vojtko, Dean's office of the Faculty of Arts & Sciences, in August 1969.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Related Materials
University of Pittsburgh Division of the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1956-1972, UA.90.4.2, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains correspondence and reports pertaining to natural science faculty, facilities, and research during the existence of the Division of Research in the Natural Sciences, as well as the years immediately before its creation and after its merger with the Division of Natural Sciences. Also included are departmental meeting minutes, publication lists, and information about the planning and construction of George Hubbard Clapp Hall. In addition, there are several files containing memos and correspondence about other departments and units at the University of Pittsburgh, as well as potential public and private funding sources.
Universities and colleges -- Administration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Administrative records; Correspondence; University of Pittsburgh. Division of Research in the Natural Sciences -- Administration; Lauffer, Max A. (Max Augustus), 1914-; Longenecker, Herbert E. (Herbert Eugune), 1912-2010
- Adams, Viers - Director of the Extension Division, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Summer session schedule of classes.
- Astronomy, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Gift of telescope by Mr. Burnham Mcffat, 1958; List of research programs, 1958; Gift of theodolite by Lucy Haworth in memory of her brother, J. Frederick Haworth; Visit by Dr. Shapley, 1958.
- Allen, Alexander J. - Cyclotron, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Memo from Dr. Allen to Chancellor Litchfield concerning use of cyclotron; Letter from Dr. Stanton C. Crawford concerning plans for a proposed cyclotron, 1952.
- Arnold, Dr. James R, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Biography and plan for radiochemistry, 1956.
- Barsotti, Iacopo - Mathematics, 1951-1952, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Research papers and congratulations for recieving a Fulbright award.
- Bender, Roger S. - Physics, 1947-1948,1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Benesch, Dr. William M. - Physics, 1952-1954, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Biological Sciences, Reports and Reprints, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  List of inquiries from companies for packaging food; list of papers published by faculty; list of research papers; minutes of staff conferences; annual report, 1950/1951, 1952/1953, 1955/1956; research report of the Deptarment of Biological Sciences, 1950.
- Biological Sciences, Subjects, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Departmental budget; Pymatuning budget, 1957-1958; campus mail; personnel; Physical Plant, including Cathedral of Learning, George Hubbard Clapp Hall, and Plant Pathology Research Laboratory; proposals, 1957-1958; Staff; teaching problems; telephone system; tropical testing; microscope use fee.
- Biological Sciences, Staff Conference Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Biological Sciences - Pymatuning, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Organization at Pymatuning, 1949; pictures taken at Pymatuning; Catalog for Summer, 1951; correspondence of Doctor Robert E. Griggs; proposed outline for University prospecture on Pymatuning Field Laboratory; Pymatuning Field Laboratory Program, 1950; correspondence concerning lease from Water & Power Resources Board; partial record of activity in conservation and related fields; program for field biology in Western Pennsylvania; industry's role in the Clean Streams Program in Pennsylvania.
- Biological Sciences - Pymatuning, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Correspondence; Pymatuning Laboratory of field biology, catalog, 1958; lease agreement, 1957; annual budget, 1956; catalog, 1953, 1955; annual report, 1955; meeting minutes concerning Pymatuning Laboratory, November 29, 1954; proposal for building to house; research projects.
- Biophysics, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Personnel problems; physical plant; Biophysics at the University of Pittsburgh; Virus Research Project, Progress report, 1950; summary of research activities in the Biophysics Laboratory, 1948-1950; proposed Department of Biophysics.
- Castle, R. Woodrow, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Chemistry, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Budget, 1953-1954, 1956; Personnel problems, 1951-1956; Proposals, 1952, 1954; Teaching problems, 1951-1952, 1955.
- Chemistry, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Personnel problems, 1958; Inquiries; Fellowships, 1958; Research, 1958; Physical plant; Seminars.
- Chemistry, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Proposals for research; Minutes of staff meeting, December 1944; Research, 1946.
- Chemistry, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  A brief report on Alumni Hall, January 1950; annual report, 1948/1949-1949/1950; Research report of B. F. Daubert, 1948-1950.
- Chemistry, 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Annual report, 1952/1953, 1954/55; Chemistry at Pitt pamphlet; "Chemistry in research in the natural sciences," by Herbert E. Longenecker, 1951; Biographical outline of Alexander Silverman, Head of the Department of Chemistry, 1951; Annual research progress report, 1950/1951.
- Cox, Benjamin B., 1956-1967 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Oil geologist considered for a professorship from Gulf.
- Craig, R.S. - Physical Chemistry, Buhl Foundation, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Research progress report, 1942-1943.
- Crawford, Dr. Stanton Chapman - Secretary of the University and Dean of the College, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Correspondence, 1948-1952; Organization and operation of Research in the Natural Sciences.
- Crawford, Dr. Stanton Chapman, 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Crawford, Dr. Stanton Chapman - Dean of the Faculties, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Minutes of meeting to discuss standards of faculty appointments, April 14, 1958; Statement or criteria for appointment and promotion of faculty, Reviewed 1957; The University library system, February 24, 1958.
- Donahue, Thomas M. - Physics, 1951-1957 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Felsenfeld, Gary, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Correspondence, 1957-1958; "Studies on the formation of two and three stranded polyribonucleotides," 1957.
- Fitzgerald, Rufus Henry - Chancellor, 1951-1956 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Geology, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Inquiries; Personnel problems; Physical plant; Staff, including F.C. Macknight, Donald Groff, and N.S. Sender; Teaching.
- Gray, Peter - Biological Sciences, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Gray, Peter - Biological Sciences, 1940-1948 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Correspondence concerning research possibilities; Personnel, 1940-1948.
- Gray, Peter - Biological Sciences, 1949-1954 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Correspondence concerning research possibilities; Personnel, 1949-1954.
- Gray, Peter - Biological Sciences, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Correspondence concerning research possibilities; Personnel, 1955-1958.
- Griggs, Robert F., 1947-1957 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  Correspondence and application, 1947-1957.
- Hanig, Martin, 1950-1958 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Hofmann, Klaus - Hofmann-LaRoche Company, 1944-1953 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  Correspondence, 1944-1947, 1952-1953; Bibliography of his publications; Biographical sketch; "Synthetic biotin" paper; Recommendation that research of Chemistry Department in field of biochemistry be merged with Department of Biochemistry in the Medical School, 1952.
- Kelly, W. C. - Physics, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Lauffer, Max A., 1938-1944, 1948, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  Publications, 1938-1944; negotiations with Phipps Conservatory; Proposed Department of Biophysics, 1948; Virus Research Program; Dean in 1956; Note on "Essay on the impact of Marxism" by Josef Macek; Report of the acquisition of the Schenley Hotel and apartments; Handling and protection of classified matter of Department of Defense.
- Litchfield, Dr. Edward H. - Chancellor, 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  Correspondence, 1956-1958: Guest list for luncheon at Duquesne Club, May 26, 1958; Standards for promotion of faculty; Reorganization of Chancellor's Office; Inoculations for Asian flu; Improvement in plans for insurance and retirement benefits; background information on George Hubbard Clapp Hall; Budget matters for Division of Natural Sciences; Electron Volt Accelerator proposed.
- Litchfield, Dr. Edward H. - Chancellor, Inauguration, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  Dedication of George Hubbard Clapp Hall; Progress Reports for inauguration; Tentative proposals for Inaugural Seminars, May 21-June 14, 1956; Instructions for participants in the Inauguration procession.
- Litchfield, Dr. Edward H. - Chancellor, Inauguration Seminars in Natural Sciences, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Mathematics, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  Budget; Departmental meetings; Inquiries; Physical Plant; General correspondence.
- Mathematics, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  Personnel Problems; Recommendations of appointment; Staff; Problems.
- Montgomery, Charles E. - Physics, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Montgomery, Edison, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  Budget questions, biological sciences; sponsored research support; request for early calendar; cost estimates.
- Nutting, Charles B. - Acting Chancellor, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  Annual report of the Division of Research in the Natural Sciences, 1955/1956; Extra compensation to faculty, 1952-1956.
- Physics, 1938-1948 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  Report on the hazards of radiation; personnel; requests for equipment; "General policies relating to graduate work leading to advanced degrees in physics, 1938-1948" pamphlet; Electron microscope laboratory; Report on the activities of the cooperative x-ray laboratory, by S.S. Sidhu, 1943; Paper on research in nuclear physics.
- Physics, 1948-1953 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  Annual report, 1950/1951, 1952/1953; personnel; equipment; Conference on Medium Energy Nuclear Physics report, 1952; "Solid State Program"; Graduate work in Physics at the University pamphlet; Report on research in organic-biochemistry, submitted by Klaus Hofmann, 1950/1951; Research report, 1948-1950.
- Physics, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  Graduate work in physics, 1956; Old Mellon Institute floor plans and blue prints; Annual report, 1955/1956; Rough draft of "A request for funds for the development of physics at the University," July 1955.
- Physics, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  Status of physics at the University of Pittsburgh, 1956; "Physics at the University of Pittsburgh, A plan for development" pamphlet, 1955; Tentative plans for a physics building, August 1955.
- Physics, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  Budget; Grants and proposals, 1957; Physical plant, 1957-1958; General correspondence.
- Physics (Box 7, Folder 51)
  Teaching problems, general and Engineering physics; Physics library; Staff; Personnel problems; recommendation for appointment and appointment offers turned down; Colloquiums; Accelerator.
- Prouty, C.E. - Geology, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 52)
- Psychology (Box 7, Folder 53)
  Budget and Travel expense; Recommendation of appointment; Teaching problems; Psychology conference.
- Radiation Laboratory, 1945-1958 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  Van de Graaff Generator; Applied Radiation Corp.; Argonne National Laboratory; Radiation Laboratory dedication suggested, 1951; Proposed research & development - Wright Field, 1945; Letters about contracts; Army Air Forces contract.
- Reiser, Dr. Oliver L. - Philosophy, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  "Unified symbolism for world understanding in science" by Oliver L. Reiser, 1951; Where Karl Marx went wrong - Pantheistic humanism; Correspondence with Foundation for Integrated Education; A resolution of the "East-West problem" by way of a scientific humanism; Religion and science in conflict; A philosophy for world unification; Escape from chaos: a program of integrated education.
- Resnick, Robert, 1951-1956 (Box 7, Folder 56)
- Rosenberg, Jerome L. - Chemistry (Box 7, Folder 57)
  Question of patent, A novel method for the preparation of highly branched malonic acids submitted by Woard E. Merrill and John N. Wotiz.
- Smith, L.E. - Department of Planning and Development (Box 7, Folder 58)
  Correspondence concerning assistantships in chemistry.
- Spiess, Eliot B, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  Correspondence with Max A. Lauffer, Peter Gray, and Herbert E. Longenecker; "Chromosomal adaptive polymorphism in drosophilia persililis. I. Life cycle components under near optimal conditions" reprint, 1956.
- Stahr, Eliot B. - Vice Chancellor for the Professions, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  Correspondence with Max A. Lauffer, 1957-1959.
- Taylor, Dr. James A. - Mathematics, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  Correspondence with Max A. Lauffer and Dr. Putnam Jones.
- Vieh, Walter E. - Assistant Chancellor for Business Affairs, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 62)
- Wallace, William E. - Chemistry, 1942-1958 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  Correspondence and memos, 1942-1958.
- Weber, John - Secretary of the University, 1951-1956 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  Correspondence, 1952-1956; Retirement policy; Status of graduate student assistants, 1956; "Industrial security manual for safeguarding classified security information" pamphlet, 1951.
- Wertman, Kenneth - Biological Sciences, 1950-1957 (Box 8, Folder 65)
- Wotiz, John H. - Chemistry, 1950-1957 (Box 8, Folder 66)
- Admissions, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  High school visitation program,1958-1959; "Higher education's battle of the bulge" by Edwin H. Beachler.
- Allegheny Observatory, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  Correspondence, 1951-1957; Keeler Memorial telescope; reprints of Kevin Burns.
- Argonne National Laboratory, Participating Universities, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 69)
- Atomic Energy Commission, 1951-1957 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  Correspondence, 1951-1957:; Suggested course in use of radio-isotopes for research; Index to major activities in atomic energy programs, 1955-1956; Manual for control of government property in possession of non-profit research and development contractors; Revised guide for the submission of research proposals, February 1954; Survey reports on educational, scientific, and engineering manpower, 1957.
- Student Council of Religious Organizations, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 71)
- Religion (Box 8, Folder 72)
  Correspondence of Chaplain Luccock; "Religion at Pitt" pamphlet; Interdepartmental major.
- Buhl Planetarium, School Science Fair Programs, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 73)
- Class Cards, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  Concern over grades in Chemistry; Grade distribution, 1956.
- Chemical Engineering, Suggested Research Projects (Box 9, Folder 75)
- Committee on Community Services, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 76)
- Committee on Training in Nuclear Research and Engineering, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  Summary of conference regarding campus-side utilization of small and intermediate sized reactor, 1957; Discussion of a plan for a multibillion volt proton accelerator, 1956; Van de Graaff type accelerator; Mrs. Scaife gave $100,000; Proposal for cooperation with Technology; Report of Committee; Minutes of meeting, March 21, 1956.
- Committees: Heinz Educational Fund; Educational; Policies; Radiation (Box 9, Folder 78)
  Hazards; Travel reimbursement; Retirement from administrative duties; Bicentennial Science Committee; Faculty Committee on Publications; Committee on Administrative Retirement
- Search Committee for Vice Chancellor for Health Professions (Box 9, Folder 79)
- Search Committee for Vice Chancellor for the Disciplines, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 80)
- Council of Deans (Box 9, Folder 81)
  Memos concerning meetings; Bibliographical Circular for the Council of Deans; Proposed organization of Graduate study; Statement of criteria for appointment and promotion of faculty; Statement of policy on retirement from administrative assignments.
- Coal Research Board, Department of Mines - Joseph T. Kennedy, Secretary (Box 10, Folder 82)
- The College - Dr. John Geise, Dean, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 83)
  Notices, 1957-1958; Correspondence, 1957-1958; Administrative Officers to retire at 65; Interdisciplinary Seminar in College Teaching, 1957/1958; General correspondence, 1956-1957.
- Upper Campus Buildings Committee, 1954-1955 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  Recommendations for future expansion of the Schools of Engineering and Mines, 1955; Correspondence of Dean Fitterer, Dean Longenecker, Dr. Crawford, Dr. Lauffer, and Mr.Fisher concerning new building; Minutes of meeting to initiate studies on building facilities for Schools other than Health Group, 1953; Report on Upper Dental Building, November 26, 1954; 2 maps of Oakland area.
- Upper Campus Buildings Committee, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  Old Mellon Institute to be used for Physics, 1958; "Physics at the University of Pittsburgh, plans for development" pamphlet; Proposed physics building; Report of the Committee, 1956; Radiation Laboratory space needs space and Old Mellon Institute; Costs to alter Old Mellon Institute; Lorena Garloch's letter asking for book storage space.
- Westinghouse, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 86)
  Science Teachers' Day; Westinghouse nuclear program at University of Pittsburgh, 1956.
- Computer - Mellon Institute, 1952,1957 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  Report on conference about the use of the IBM 650 for crystal structure analysis computations, 1957; The IBM type 650 computer; Statement of the University of Pittsburgh in support of a proposal of Mellon Institute of Industrial Research to house, maintain, and operate a digital computer for the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, October 22, 1952; Consideration of a minimal calculating machine.
- Core Curriculum, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  Memo to Members of the Science Core Committee, 1957; Address at special meeting to discuss the core curriculum, November 28, 1958; Memo for Committee on admissions, curriculum, and educational policies about the core curriculum, October 20, 1956.
- Department Heads Meetings, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  Meeting minutes, 1956-1958; Notices of meetings; Apartments available in Schenley Compound, 1957; Preliminary statement of criteria for appointment and promotion of Faculty, June 1957; Memo on University scholarship committee.
- Directory Cards for Natural Sciences, 1954-1957 (Box 10, Folder 90)
- Draft Deferment for Staff and Students, 1956, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 91)
- Departmental Annual Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 92)
- Selective Service, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 93)
  Memos about the draft and deferment, 1952.
- Engineering and Mines - G.R. Fitterer, Dean, 1955-1957 (Box 11, Folder 94)
- Department of Biophysics, Executive Committee, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 95)
- General Science Seminar, 1954-1956 (Box 11, Folder 96)
  To observe the 10th anniversary of the establishment of Research in the Natural Sciences at the University of Pittsburgh, 1954/1955-1955/1956.
- History Department, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 97)
  Memos, 1945; One day conference on the history of science and technology; Dr. Arthur M. Schlesinger, speaker.
- Internships and Fellowships, 1956-1959 (Box 11, Folder 98)
  New fellowships for graduate study, 1957; Danforth teacher grants, 1958-1959; Southern fellowships Fund, 1955/1956; American Association of University Women; Fellowships for women, 1956/1957; National Science Foundation fellowships, 1957.
- Buhl Foundation, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 99)
  Correspondence concerning the gift toward the George Hubbard Clapp Hall; Plan to increase basic research budget of Department of Biophysics; Memo by Dr. Herbert Longenecker concerning Pittsburgh as the scientific capital of the world; Grant of $45,000 to finance a two-year program of cooperative scientific research; Minutes of the Research Committee meeting; correspondence with Dr. C.G. King concerning research in biochemistry, 1935; A coordinated program of fundamental research in biochemistry prepared by Dr. Alexander Silverman, 1936; photographs of the Plant Virus Laboratory and Dr. W. Conway Price; Measuring nuclear reaction and Dr. David Halliday; Plant physiology laboratory; Electron microscope gift of George Hubbard Clapp; Beta-ray Spectrometer; Dr. M.A. Lauffer; Collins Helium Cryostat and Dr. W. E. Wallace.
- Future Scientists of America Foundation, Applicant Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 100)
- National Science Foundation, 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  Federal grants and contracts for unclassified research in the physical sciences, 1956; Fellowships and Grants folders; Correspondence concerning grants, 1955-1958.
- National Science Foundation, Teacher Training Program, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  Correspondence, pamphlets, and brochures.
- Gulf Research and Development Co., 1952 (Box 11, Folder 103)
  Pittsburgh's place in the world of scientific and technological education and research; A plan for industry liaison and cooperation with the research program in the physical sciences at the University of Pittsburgh, October 1952.
- Office of Naval Research, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 104)
  Contractor's Manual, January 1956; Ordnance Research Bulletin, September 1955; "Employment opportunities, Department Of Navy, Bureau of Ordnance" pamphlet; Research and development in the U. S. Army, Contractor's Guide.
- Research Corporation, N.Y., 1954,1956 (Box 12, Folder 105)
  Correspondence concerning Dr. Robert Levine's discovery and having it patented; The arylation and alkylation of malonic esters, 1956; New instrument for measuring noise, developed by Kenneth C. Stewart, 1954.
- National Academy of Sciences, National Research Council., 1956-1958 (Box 12, Folder 106)
- Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, Program for Basic Research., 1955-1958 (Box 12, Folder 107)
- Rockefeller Foundation, 1952, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 108)
  Proposal for an expanded program in radiobiology at the University of Pittsburgh, 1957; request for a grant for Robert J. Walker project, 1952.
- Ford Foundation, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 109)
  News from the Ford Foundation; Dr. Longenecker's visit to seek funds; Research proposal to the behavioral sciences division, 1953; Ford Foundation again to offer foreign-area study fellowships.
- Foundations, General Information, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 110)